ATTENBOROUGH: Our planet may be home to
30 million different kinds
of animals and plants,
each individual locked in
its own lifelong fight for survival.
Everywhere you look,
on land or in the ocean,
there are extraordinary examples
of the lengths
living things go to to stay alive.
This is the coast of Florida.
Here, strange scars on the sea bed
hint at one animal's
remarkable strategy.
These are bottlenose dolphins,
one of the most
intelligent animals on Earth.
Their prey is very elusive,
fast-swimming fish.
But the dolphins have invented
a completely new way of hunting.
By beating its tail down hard,
this dolphin stirs up the shallow silt.
And by swimming in a tight circle,
it creates a ring of mushrooming mud
around a shoal of fish.
The contracting ring traps the fish
just like a net.
Panicked, the fish jump to escape,
right into the open mouths
of the waiting dolphins.
Again and again,
the lead dolphin creates a circle
before they all line up
with perfect timing.
These dolphins are the only ones
known to have developed
this hunting behaviour,
and it gives them an edge.
This sort of advantage
may mean the difference
between life and death
in the survival of the fittest.
This series reveals the most
spectacular and extraordinary strategies
that animals and plants have developed
to stay alive.
For every creature,
every day is full of challenges,
all of which must be overcome,
somehow, in order to survive.
Kenya, famous for its big cats,
the supreme hunters.
Cheetahs specialise in hunting at speed.
Though fast, they are fragile creatures,
built to sprint after small prey.
They don't have the strength
or weight of a lion
to bring down larger animals.
This male is different.
He doesn't hunt alone.
He's learnt that
there is strength in numbers.
But here, there are not just two,
but three cheetahs.
A band of brothers.
They have changed their tactics
and by doing so
have taken their prey by surprise.
They have learnt that working together,
they can bring down large prey.
An ostrich.
A bird that towers over a cheetah
and is more than twice as heavy.
It can't fly to escape danger,
but it can lash out with a deadly kick.
A female, unaware as yet of any danger.
Even with three of them,
this is still highly risky.
If one gets injured,
the other two couldn't hope
to tackle such large prey.
On the other hand,
if they get it right,
the rewards are huge.
(CAWING)
The male has spotted
one of the brothers, but only one.
It's not too worried.
Then suddenly, there are three!
(OSTRICH SCREECHING)
The female is slower
to realise the danger,
and the cheetahs switch targets.
(CAWING)
(CHEETAHS GROWLING)
It takes the combined effort
and weight of all three brothers
to bring down this powerful bird.
Even now, the ostrich
could land a fatal kick.
(CHEETAH BREATHING HEAVILY)
So far, the brothers are winning.
Ostriches have yet to
find a way to foil such tactics.
Other animals have also evolved
surprising tactics
to outmanoeuvre the enemy,
not with brute strength,
but with extraordinary weapons.
Madagascar.
A strange world
where nothing is quite as it seems.
To hunt here requires
stealth and subterfuge.
And living within the trees
is a master of ambush,
a praying mantis.
Well-camouflaged and lightning-quick,
these insects are
highly efficient predators.
But even they are outgunned.
A chameleon.
Its camouflage is exceptional
because it can change its skin colour
to match its surroundings.
Its eyes move independently
to spot prey.
It creeps towards its victim
until just in range.
Then it unleashes a super weapon.
Its tongue shoots out at
1 5 metres per second
and not only hits,
but grasps, its target.
But few hunters are always successful.
For them, a hunt is just one meal.
For prey, the stakes are higher.
It's life or death.
As Antarctica moves
from spring into summer,
the inlets and bays
once choked with ice become free
and animals move in to feed.
These are crabeater seals.
They don't actually eat crabs,
but krill, small shrimps that swarm
in their billions in these waters.
(SEAL BARKING)
(SNORTING)
Resting on a large ice floe,
these crabeaters are safe.
But as soon as they enter the water,
they are on their guard,
for good reason.
Killer whales.
Here in Antarctica,
many killer whales prey only on fish.
But these whales are different,
they specialise in hunting seals.
This seal, swimming to open water,
is unaware of
the danger heading his way.
Until now.
He's in real trouble.
There is no escape
unless he can hide behind
this small piece of floating ice.
But he's been spotted, and surrounded.
Now agility is his only chance.
He dodges for his life, staying
as close as he can to the iceberg.
He's tiring,
and the whales tighten the circle,
going for the kill.
But hunters don't always
get their own way.
In the end, the seal's
determination and skill,
using the ice for protection,
kept him just out of reach.
And the whales move on.
Recently, it's been observed
that killer whales
are much more successful
when hunting other types of seal.
Crabeaters like this
put up too much of a fight.
For creatures living in the open ocean,
there is nowhere to hide from predators.
But there is safety in numbers.
One fish, however,
has evolved a different escape tactic,
to leave the water completely,
take to the air and fly!
After a huge effort to get airborne,
flying fish can glide 200 metres or so
to escape the predators chasing them.
(INSECTS CHIRPING)
Not all animals are hunters,
many are vegetarians.
But the battle between
animals and plants
can also be intense.
Boa Vista, central Brazil.
This valley is peppered
with strangely pitted rocks.
(BIRD SQUAWKING)
These are not natural formations,
but the legacy of a long struggle
between one animal and one plant.
Brown tufted capuchins,
highly intelligent monkeys.
They spend their nights
in the safety of caves,
emerging each morning to find food.
Down in the valley is
a particular favourite,
a nut palm.
The palms produce huge seeds,
but they have very strong shells
that protect them against
attack from hungry animals.
For the capuchins,
this is a war of attrition.
They check which seed is the ripest
and the battle commences.
The first job is to tear the tough,
fibrous husk from the nut.
He doesn't try to
crack the nut straightaway,
but drops it to the ground.
He's learnt that a nut should be given
a week or so drying in the sun.
These are ones he prepared earlier.
He taps them to see if they're ready.
This huge, flat rock is his anvil.
(MONKEYS CHITTERING)
And this is a hammer.
It's made of a different and
much harder rock than the anvil.
Now something extraordinary happens.
The capuchins' use of these stone tools
requires an exceptional level of
intelligence, planning and dexterity.
The nut finally cracks
and exposes a rich, oily kernel.
Youngsters watch and imitate the adults,
just as human toddlers do.
If they are to become independent,
they must learn to crack their own nuts.
But the learning process is long,
with many frustrations.
They learn early on that
to do a job properly,
you need the right tool.
It can take eight years
for a capuchin to master this art
and overcome the palm's
formidable defences.
But some plants have turned
the tables and feed on animals.
This is a highly sophisticated trap.
The bait, sugary nectar
around the rim of the disc.
The triggers, fine hairs,
two of which have to be touched
within 20 seconds of each other.
(FLY BUZZING)
The victim, a fly,
which finds the colour
and nectar irresistible.
One...
Two.
When triggered,
the trap snaps shut so fast
that the fly is imprisoned.
The Venus Flytrap now
slowly digests its victim.
Life's challenges are
more than just finding food.
In every animal's life,
there comes a time
when its mind turns to breeding.
One creature's approach
is mind-boggling.
Malaysia.
This strange insect has been
lying dormant on the forest floor.
Once safe in the trees,
these males hide among the leaves
and begin
an extraordinary transformation,
one that will make the difference
between fathering offspring or not.
He begins by gulping in air bubbles,
forcing them up into his head.
(BUBBLING)
He then pumps the bubbles
into the stalks supporting his eyes,
just like blowing up a balloon.
And this is what earns
these creatures their name,
the stalk-eyed fly.
A few final adjustments
to straighten out any remaining creases
and he's ready for action.
They may look unwieldy,
but eyes on stalks
improve not only
his ability to spot predators,
but they are key
when it comes to winning females.
In the evening,
both males and females gather,
and the males begin to
size one another up,
eyeball to eyeball.
Having the widest eye span
puts you at the top
of the pecking order.
The eye stalks are not weapons,
they're measuring sticks,
used to gauge how big,
and so how strong, a male is.
But there's trouble if two top males
have exactly the same eye width,
then the contest descends into a brawl.
Defeated.
The winner.
He now has the right to mate
with all the females nearby.
The rather gentlemanly way
stalk-eyed flies settle
their differences over females
is not the only way.
Some animals are much more violent.
It's the dry season in Zambia.
The lagoons are either baked dry
or the mud is so thick
animals get stuck,
with fatal consequences.
This male hippo has been
living in one small lagoon
but as it dries,
it's turning into a death trap.
Understandably, the females that
once shared it with him have all left.
Even if he wants to,
he can't stay much longer.
He needs water to keep cool
and females to mate with.
And this is where they all are.
Almost all the hippos in the area
are now in what is left
of the Luangwa River,
because it's the last place
where there's still deep water.
This bend is controlled by
an all-powerful male.
Since the drought, many more females
have joined his herd.
(HIPPO GRUNTING)
They are happy to live cheek by jowl,
but any male who comes here
in the hope of mating
must first defeat the overlord.
The wandering male arrives
and has a decision to make,
submit or fight.
Victory for the overlord.
His domination of his channel
in the river remains
and with it,
mating rights with the females.
The loser is alive, but is an outcast.
He retreats to another part of the river
where it is so shallow
that no females will follow.
His chance to father offspring is over,
for now.
For some animals,
the challenges of breeding
are not about fighting,
but about courtship.
Among birds, displays, songs and rituals
can reach extraordinary levels
of complexity and beauty.
During spring
on the freshwater lakes of Oregon,
grebes join together to
renew their partnership.
The ceremony starts with
a series of graceful duets,
in which one partner echoes
the actions of the other.
But the real test comes now.
Only the strongest and the most faithful
are prepared to join together
for the final exultant dance.
Those animals which have young
now face a whole new set of challenges
to protect and nurture their offspring.
In the cold waters of the northern
Pacific Ocean, there lives a giant.
A giant Pacific octopus,
at over four metres long.
She is hunting, not for prey,
but for a den.
Somewhere to settle down and hide.
Her den has to be just right.
She is going to live here
for the rest of her life.
She's carrying fertilised eggs,
and now, happy and settled,
she lays them,
1 00,000 of them.
Over the next six months,
she carefully tends her precious brood.
She caresses them with her arms
to keep them free of algae
and properly supplied with oxygen.
This is her first and only brood
and so she takes great care of them.
While she's guarding her eggs,
she doesn't leave the den.
Not once.
Unable to feed, she is starving.
Her last act of devotion
is to blow water over the eggs
to help them hatch.
Young, fully-developed octopus pop out.
Though only a few will survive
to adulthood,
she has given them
the best chance she can.
After her long and lonely vigil,
she is dead.
Surely this sacrifice must make her
one of nature's most devoted mothers.
Here, 30 metres beneath
the Costa Rican forest canopy,
another dedicated mother
ensures that her young
also have the best possible start
in life.
This tiny strawberry poison arrow frog,
only the size of a fingernail,
is guarding her fertilised eggs.
Whilst the eggs and tadpoles
are developing,
she and her mate keep watch,
making sure that
they are safe from predators.
But they can't stay here forever.
The leaf litter is drying out
and tadpoles need water.
She must do something, and fast.
She needs to move them,
and so encourages one tadpole
to climb on her back.
She now begins an epic journey.
But it's not to a pond,
as you might expect,
she is looking for
something very particular.
Her journey takes her
across the forest floor
to the foot of a tall tree.
And then she starts to climb.
For such a little frog,
it is a marathon ascent,
like a human mother climbing
the Empire State Building
with a child on her back.
She's looking for a plant, a bromeliad,
growing on the tree.
It holds a pool of water at its centre,
the perfect nursery pool
for a developing tadpole.
In slides her youngster.
But this is only one of six tadpoles.
She must rush back down
to rescue the others.
One by one, she collects them
and carries each to its own bromeliad.
But there is another problem.
The little pools contain no food.
So she has to provide it.
She lays an unfertilised egg
in each pool for her tadpoles to eat.
And then she leaves.
But one egg won't sustain
a growing tadpole for long,
so she has to return every few days
with another egg.
Over the next two weeks,
she can climb almost half a mile
tending her young,
an astonishing feat
for such a tiny creature.
While she is busy delivering eggs,
the tadpole grows legs
and its tail begins to disappear.
And then, one day, it leaves
its bromeliad nursery forever
and climbs out into the forest,
whilst its mother has
a well-deserved rest.
(WIND HOWLING)
Birds are also diligent parents.
Over their lifetime, they invest
huge effort in just a few young.
(ALL SQUAWKING)
But there is only so much
a parent can do.
All along the Antarctic Peninsula,
both male and female chinstrap penguins
have been commuting daily
from the open ocean
to collect food for their chicks.
Mouthfuls of krill,
caught many miles away at sea,
are regurgitated.
But one day
the chicks wait in vain for food.
Their parents do not return.
The chicks now face life on their own.
This is the toughest time
in an animal's life,
and some are not going to make it.
Over the next few days,
driven by hunger,
the chicks make their way
down to the shore.
Instinct tells them
they have to head out to sea.
Built to withstand the cold,
they have already accumulated
a layer of fat
and their outer feathers
act as a waterproof shield.
But they still have to learn to swim.
The polar sea is challenging enough,
but with a change in the wind,
a slick of broken ice
has choked the bay.
For any penguin,
this ice presents a real problem.
But for the chicks, it's a disaster.
They must get through this barrier
to the open water if they are to feed.
One, perhaps hungrier
or braver than the rest,
leads the way
and tries skittering over the top
while the others watch.
The ice is hard to swim through,
and progress is painfully slow.
(SQUAWKING)
A leopard seal.
This chick never had the chance
to learn how to avoid the seal.
Its end is inevitable.
The leopard seal
efficiently flays the chick,
tearing off a small piece
with each throw.
Others take their chance.
But the leopard seal is now ready
for its next victim.
It's a lottery, and the lucky chicks
make it out to open water.
There is still an element
of chance in life
which an individual can do little about.
In the end,
overcoming life's challenges,
whether finding enough to eat
or outwitting your predators,
is only significant if
life's final challenge can be met.
From a tiny frog dedicating weeks
to her few cherished tadpoles
to an orang-utan who spends eight years
bringing up her baby,
individual animals strive to
reach this one ultimate goal,
to pass on their genes
and to ensure the survival
of the next generation.
Ultimately, in nature,
that is what life is all about.
During the three years it took
to film Life,
our camera crews visited
every continent on Earth,
but the most challenging was Antarctica.
Here, filming was only possible
with the help of an extraordinary range
of people and organisations.
An Air Force jet delivering supplies
to McMurdo Research Station
ferried one of our crews
to the Ross Ice Shelf.
And on the other side of the continent,
a team sailed for five days
across the Drake Passage
to reach the Antarctic Peninsula.
Once there, a small crew was
put ashore on Deception Island
to spend a month camping on the edge
of a penguin colony.
Two people and 200,000 penguins.
Another team joined
scientists drilling through the ice
to explore the beautiful
and bizarre world below.
But the hardest and most ambitious shoot
involved four film crews,
a celebrated French yachtsman
and the Ministry of Defence.
The teams had a two-month window
to film Antarctica's two top predators
in action.
We knew that one could be found
prowling the coast of Rosenthal Island,
waiting for young penguins
to take their first plunge.
And the man to take us there
was Jerome Poncet.
He skippered the first yacht
to sail south of the Antarctic Circle
and has been back every year
for the past 35.
He knows Antarctic sailing
like no one else.
Not good at all.
His yacht, The Golden Fleece,
is not an ice-breaker
but Jerome has his own unique way
of getting through.
He shunts one floe against another
to clear a way through,
like playing marbles.
Jerome, once he gets his teeth
into a situation,
he doesn't like to let it go.
So, maybe we'll be here
for a few hours yet.
ATTENBOROUGH: Jerome is determined
to get through this channel.
And you talk about
hundreds and hundreds of turns.
Maybe a thousand turns
for this floe at the moment.
With the polar waters, you have to push.
ATTENBOROUGH:
Some marbles are just too big.
For now,Jerome is foiled
and has to moor for the night.
For him, tying up to 1 00,000 tons of ice
is just another day at the office.
Progress is slow.
But they need to get to Rosenthal
before the penguins leave.
They make it through
and the penguins are still there.
Chinstrap penguin chicks fledge
at a particular time of year.
The crew knew this would
draw leopard seals like a magnet.
Leopard seals are giants
among their kind.
They have teeth bigger than a lion
and a mouth than can open
nearly 1 80 degrees.
How close can Doug get?
With this seal, very.
He loses interest in his reflection
and goes back to eating penguins.
That was very exciting.
He was a super seal.
Super seal give you lots of action,
nice and close.
But I must admit, you do have to
feel sorry for the penguin.
Just doesn't stand a chance.
ATTENBOROUGH: The team knew
where to find leopard seals
but finding the other top predator
was going to be another matter entirely.
Very little is known about
Antarctic killer whales.
Time to bring in reinforcements.
HMS Endurance,
the Royal Navy's ice patrol ship.
She surveys Antarctic waters
and the crew, she changes every year.
A latest chart of this area,
we are now six miles
inside an ice shelf,
which just goes to show
how much retraction
of this ice shelf has occurred
over the past five or six years.
Would you get complications...
Series producer Martha Holmes
and cameraman David Baillie
were on board to find and film
the killer whales from the air.
Endurance carries two Lynx helicopters,
used to assist
the British Antarctic Survey
and the Hydrographic Office.
On this trip,
some time on one of the helicopters
is assigned to the Life team.
No one has succeeded
in filming killer whales
hunting off
the Antarctic Peninsula before.
Our two teams have just a few days
when they can film together.
At water level,
The Golden Fleece has exciting news.
They've found killer whales which look
as though they could be hunting.
Navy 4 35, Navy 4 35.
This is Golden Fleece,
Golden Fleece, over.
SMITH ON RADIO: Whale or orca.
This could be it. Over.
HOLMES ON RADIO:
Copy that. We're on our way.
Now it's getting really windy
where we are.
We'll be pretty lucky to
stay with them through this.
We'll give a good try, though.
4 35, this is Golden Fleece.
We have lost sight of the orca.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER ON RADIO)
We have one.
HOLMES: Yeah. They're in direct line
with that iceberg now.
Between us and the iceberg,
about 1 00 metres to the side of it.
MAN: Visual. We have visual.
ATTENBOROUGH: From the air,
the helicopter team
can follow the killer whales
more easily than the boat team.
4 35, this is Golden Fleece. Copy. Out.
ATTENBOROUGH: By working together,
the helicopter and yacht
are able to keep track of the whales
in the rough sea.
MAN ON RADIO: There are four now,
actually, yeah.
Four... Four I can see.
ATTENBOROUGH: A change in the weather
gives the chance to film at last.
They've gone further up this way.
If we follow them, that's good.
But will they hunt?
Here we go. Okay, they're coming close.
(ExCLAIMS) Yeah, they...
One, two, three, four, five, six...
It's a good 1 2, huh? Easy.
Doug has spotted
a crabeater seal near some ice.
But have the killer whales seen it?
DOUG: Just keep nosing in
this way is fine.
ATTENBOROUGH: They have.
Some good action.
Can we go closer?
It's over. That's it, they've got him.
It's still there!
ATTENBOROUGH: For a wildlife cameraman,
there are always surprises.
It has taken two months
but they've succeeded,
thanks to extraordinary collaboration,
from an entire ship's company
to a lone skipper.
Collaborations like this
would be the foundation
of the whole three years' filming
across the world.